Mr. Big. Mr. Big is a technique mostly
used in Canada, and it consists of the
police creating a fake criminal
organization to seduce the suspect into
joining it. They pretend to have a
casual encounter and start building
rapport with him, eventually leading to
a highly paid job offer for small
criminal activities such as delivering
light drugs. These tasks grow in
importance and frequency, and he's
treated as an upandcomer in the
organization. The suspect is eventually
led to Mr. Big, the fake criminal
organization's kingpin, who is actually
a highly skilled undercover
interrogator. Using threats, Mr. Big
tells the suspect that he received
incriminating information about him from
the police and that his arrest could
threaten the gang. He then offers the
suspect to clear up his situation. But
to do that, he needs to know what the
[music] suspect actually did, which
makes him confess. The final meeting is
obviously recorded, and when the
confession is done, the whole fake
criminal organization reveals itself as
the police, and he gets arrested. This
technique is usually used as a last
resort as it could sometimes cause false
confessions out of fear for Mr. Big or
to keep the lavish lifestyle that the
fake criminal organization has offered
him. Good cop and bad cop. Also called
the mut and Jeff technique. It consists
of two people taking two opposite
approaches to the interrogated person.
One interrogator adopts a hostile
approach emphasizing threats of
punishment while the other one adopts a
more sympathetic one emphasizing reward
in order to convince the interrogated
person to cooperate. The good cop then
starts defending the subject from the
bad cop's threats and accusations. This
makes the subject feel like he can
cooperate with the good cop either out
of trust or out of fear of the bad one.
This technique, however, has two
disadvantages. It can be easily spotted
and the bad cop could alienate the
subject. Read technique. The read
technique consists of a three-phase
process. The interviewer starts with a
fact analysis, then goes into a behavior
analysis, and after that, if
appropriate, the interviewer goes on
with Reed's nine steps of interrogation.
It is appropriate to go on with the nine
steps only if the first two phases show
information that indicates that the
subject is involved in the commission of
the crime. The interrogation is an
accusatory process different from the
usual question and answer format being
kind of a monologue made by the
interviewer that tells the subject that
the results of investigations clearly
show he's guilty. In the whole
interrogation process, the interviewer
keeps a calm and understanding demeanor
with the goal of making the subject
gradually more comfortable with telling
the truth. This specific part is done by
the investigator who offers various
psychological reasons that justify the
subject's behavior. First of all, the
interviewer lets the suspect know that
investigations lead to him as a
potential suspect and asks him why the
offense took place, giving him an early
opportunity to confess. Then, the
interviewer tries to shift the blame
from the suspect to some other person or
set of circumstances that made the
suspect commit the crime,
psychologically justifying his actions.
While he does all of this, the
interviewer tries to minimize the
suspect's denials until the suspect
gives a reason for why he did or didn't
commit the crime, which the interviewer
uses to move towards the acknowledgement
of what the suspect did. He then uses
body language techniques like eye
contact or proximity to assure that the
suspect is receptive. And when he's
listening, the interviewer once again
psychologically justifies his actions.
If the suspect cries at this point, the
interviewer can deduce that he might be
feeling guilty for committing the crime.
After that, the interviewer poses what's
called the alternative question, which
consists of giving two choices for what
happened, one more socially acceptable
than the other. At this point, the
suspect is expected to choose one of
them, usually the most socially
acceptable one. But whichever he
chooses, he's admitting his guilt. If he
admits it, the interviewer leads the
suspect to repeat the admission of guilt
in front of witnesses and starts testing
the validity of the confession. Lastly,
the interviewer documents the suspect's
admission or confession. Minimization,
maximization. These are two variations
of the same tactic. In minimization, the
interviewer makes the crime look smaller
than it truly is, making the suspect
more inclined to confess as he starts
thinking that he might get a smaller
punishment than he originally thought.
In maximization, the interviewer makes
the crime look bigger than it is and
starts stating the most severe
punishments applicable to the offense,
making the suspect believe he'll get a
smaller sentence if he confesses. This
one is also a pretty controversial
technique, and it could lead to false
confessions. Informal questioning.
Sometimes police officers prefer to do
field interviews without arresting
people so they don't have to read
Miranda writes. This masks an actual
interview with a normal and informal
conversation while the officer might
actually be obtaining important
information from the suspect. Another
technique similar to this one is the
change of scenery technique which
consists in the interviewer and suspect
moving away from the formal environment
where the actual interview happened and
in the interviewer asking questions in
an informal [music] way to the suspect.
This makes him feel like he left the
interrogation behind and he never
notices that he's still being
questioned. The pause technique. After
the suspect answers a question, the
interviewer remains silent and maintains
eye contact. This makes the suspect feel
like he has to share more information.
And the more he does, the better the
chance he contradicts either himself or
any known fact obtained through
evidence. Peace technique. The peace
technique is a five-stage process that
was created after the realization that
psychologically coercive techniques
often led to false confessions. It's
more of a dialogue between the
interviewer and the suspect where the
latter is let free to give their version
of what happened uninterruptedly before
presenting him with any evidence of
inconsistencies or contradictions. Its
goal is to obtain a full account of
events rather than just seeking a
confession. The first of the five stages
is planning and preparation, which
requires investigators to find out as
much as they can about the incident
under investigation, including who needs
to be interviewed and why. The second
stage is called engage and explain. And
in this one, the interviewer tries to
build rapport with the suspect. And it's
done by asking the suspect how they'd
like to be addressed, how much time they
have for the interview, or by giving him
reassurance if he seems anxious. The
third stage, called account,
clarification, and challenge, is the one
where the interviewer tries to obtain a
full account of events from the subject
without interrupting. Once the subject
has explained what happened, the
interviewer can ask follow-up questions
and eventually, in cases of
contradictory information, even
challenge the suspect's story. The
fourth stage is called closure and it
involves summarizing what the suspect
has said to ensure that there's a mutual
understanding between both parties. It
also involves verifying that everything
that needs to be discussed has been
covered. The last stage is called
evaluation and it requires the
interviewer to examine if they got what
they wanted from the interview, how the
investigation has changed with the new
information and what could have been
done better in the interview itself. As
the name says, this technique is much
more peaceful and focuses on building
rapport with the suspect to encourage
cooperation. Rapid fire. One or more
interrogators start asking rapid fire
questions in such a manner that the
suspect does not have time to answer a
question completely before the next one
is asked. This confuses him and makes
him contradict himself as he has little
time to formulate his answers. The
interrogators then proceed to question
him about those contradictions. Pride
and ego down. This one consists of
attacking the suspect's sense of
personal worth, which could lead to an
attempt to redeem his pride by
cooperating. This technique is most
effective when used against suspects who
have shown emotional weakness or
feelings of inferiority. But it's also
pretty risky as if it fails, the
interviewer has a much harder time
switching to another approach without
losing his credibility. Repetition. To
make the suspect give a full and candid
answer, the interrogator keeps asking
the same questions and repeating the
suspect's answers so that he gets so
bored that he gives a full answer in an
attempt to avoid further questions by
the interrogator. Loaded questions.
Loaded questions implicitly assume that
certain facts are true. If used with
psychologically exhausted suspects, this
technique could produce both
unintentional slip-ups that reveal the
truth or completely false confessions.
Establish your identity. The suspect is
told that some higher authorities have
identified him as a dangerous criminal
with really serious charges. So that in
an attempt to correct this mistake
against the interrogator's perpetual
denials, he provides true statements
about what actually